Do you ever feel completely overwhelmed
هل تشعرون بالعجز التام
when you're faced with a complex problem?
عندما تواجهون مشكلة متشعبة جداً ؟
Well, I hope to change that in less than three minutes.
حسناً .. اتمنى أن أغير وجهة نظركم في هذا الخصوص في أقل من ثلاث دقائق
So, I hope to convince you that complex
لذا أتمنى أن أقنعكم أن الشئ المتشعب ..
doesn't always equal complicated.
لا يعني دوماً التعقيد ..
So for me, a well-crafted baguette, fresh out of the oven,
بالنسبة لي .. الرغيف الفرنسي الطازج الخارج من الفرن
is complex,
متشعب..
but a curry onion green olive poppy cheese bread
بينما خبز البصل والزيتون الاخضر بالجبن ..
is complicated.
هو التعقيد..
I'm an ecologist, and I study complexity. I love complexity.
انا عالم بيئي .. انا ادرس التشعب .. وانا احب التشعب
And I study that in the natural world, the interconnectedness of species.
وانا ادرس هذا التعقيد .. في الطبيعة .. في العلاقات بين الفصائل
So here's a food web,
ها هي شبكة غذائية ..
or a map of feeding links between species
او شبكة تغذية الفصائل فيما بينها ..
that live in Alpine Lakes in the mountains of California.
والتي - الفصائل - تعيش في بحيرة ألبين في جبال كاليفورنيا
And this is what happens to that food web
وهذا ما يحدث لتلك الشبكة الغذائية
when it's stocked with non-native fish that never lived there before.
عندما يتم ادخال نوع جديد من الاسماك لم يكن موجوداً من ذي قبل
All the grayed-out species disappear.
فكما نرى سوف تختفي كل الفصائل التي تم تحديدها باللون الفضي
Some are actually on the brink of extinction.
وبعضها سوف يتعرض للانقراض
And lakes with fish have more mosquitos, even though they eat them.
والبحيرة التي تعيش فيها الاسماك . نلاحظ فيها وجود البعوض اكثر .. رغم ان الاسماك تأكل البعوض
These effects were all unanticipated,
ان هذه النتائج والآثار كلها كانت غير متوقعة ..
and yet we're discovering they're predictable.
ولكننا اليوم نتوصل الى طرق لتوقعها وتحديدها
So I want to share with you a couple key insights
إذا اريد اليوم ان اشارككم بمعلومتين
about complexity we're learning from studying nature
تعلمانهم من التشعب الموجود في الطبيعة ..
that maybe are applicable to other problems.
والتي يمكنك ان تطبق على المشاكل الاخرى
First is the simple power of good visualization tools
الاولى هي .. قوة العرض البصري للمشكلة ..
to help untangle complexity
وهي طريقة ناجعة لفك التشعب
and just encourage you to ask questions you didn't think of before.
فالتمثيل البصري يشجعك على طرح اسئلة لم تكن تخطر ببالك من ذي قبل
For example, you could plot the flow of carbon
فعلى سبيل المثال ..يمكننا تحديد كيفية تدفق الكربون
through corporate supply chains in a corporate ecosystem,
عبر النظم الغذائية في النظام البيئي
or the interconnections of habitat patches
او ان نحدد التواصل بين الكائنات
for endangered species in Yosemite National Park.
للفصائل المعرضة للإنقراض في حديقة يوسيمت الوطنية
The next thing is that if you want to predict
والامر الثاني هو .. انه ان اردت ان تتوقع
the effect of one species on another,
أثر فصيلة على أخرى
if you focus only on that link,
فانه ان ركزت فحسب على هذه العلاقة ..
and then you black box the rest,
وقمت بتهميش العلاقات الاخرى ..
it's actually less predictable
فان التوقع والتخمين سيصبح أصعب ..
than if you step back, consider the entire system -- all the species, all the links --
من اذا قمت بالنظر من خطوة أبعد .. وبإعتبار كل النظام .. وكل الفصائل وكل الصلات
and from that place,
ومن ذلك المكان .. خارج المشكلة
hone in on the sphere of influence that matters most.
يمكننا ان نشحذ التوقع بمعلومات اكثر وتأثيرات أكبر
And we're discovering, with our research,
ونحن نكتشف تبعاً لابحاثنا
that's often very local to the node you care about
ان العقدة تتأثر على الاقل
within one or two degrees.
بمستويين أكبر من محيطها
So the more you step back, embrace complexity,
إذاً ... كلما ارتقيت إلى مستوى " وسعت دائرة التحليل "
the better chance you have of finding simple answers,
فإن امكانية الوصول الى حلول بسيطة تكبر
and it's often different than the simple answer that you started with.
وتلك الحلول عادة ماتكون حلول بسيطة .. ومختلفة عن تلك التي نتوقع
So let's switch gears and look at a really complex problem
حسناً لننظر الآن الى مشكلة واقعية متشعبة جداً ..
courtesy of the U.S. government.
تخص الحكومة الامريكية
This is a diagram of the U.S. counterinsurgency strategy in Afghanistan.
ان هذا المخطط يمثل استراتيجية مكافحة التمرد في افغانستان
It was front page of the New York Times a couple months ago.
وقد ظهر في الصفحة الاولى لجريدة نيويورك تايمز منذ شهرين
Instantly ridiculed by the media
وقد تم السخرية منه
for being so crazy complicated.
بواسطة الاعلام .. لأن تلك الاستراتيجية معقّدة جداً
And the stated goal was to increase popular support
وكان الهدف منها هو جلب الدعم الشعبي
for the Afghan government.
للحكومة الافغانية
Clearly a complex problem,
وهو امرٌ متشابك جداً كما هو واضح
but is it complicated?
ولكن هل هي معقّدة ؟
Well, when I saw this in the front page of the Times,
حسناً .. عندما رأيت هذه الصفحة في جريدة التايمز ..
I thought, "Great. Finally something I can relate to.
قلت في نفسي .. رائع .. هناك شيء يمكنني ان أصل نفسي به ..
I can sink my teeth into this."
يمكنني ان انخرط في هذا الامر حتى النخاع !
So let's do it. So here we go for the first time ever,
حسناً لنقم بالامر .. انها المرة الاولى
a world premiere view of this spaghetti diagram as an ordered network.
في العالم التي يتم استخدام هذه الشبكة " التي تشبه الاسباغتي " كشبكة منتظمة
The circled node is the one we're trying to influence --
ان هذه الدوائر هي التي نحاول أن نؤثر عليها
popular support for the government.
اي جلب الدعم الشعبي للحكومة
And so now we can look one degrees, two degrees,
وكما نرى يمكننا ان ننظر الى المشكلة .. من مستوى تواصل واحد .. الى مستويين ..
three degrees away from that node
الى ثلاث مستويات ..
and eliminate three-quarters of the diagram outside that sphere of influence.
وهذا يخرج ثلاثة ارباع المخطط من قائمة التأثير
Within that sphere,
داخل مجال التأثير هذا
most of those nodes are not actionable, like the harshness of the terrain,
الكثير من هذه العقد لا يمكن التأثير عليها .. مثل قسوة التأثير
and a very small minority are actual military actions.
والبعض منها .. والاقلية هي عمليات عسكرية
Most are non-violent and they fall into two broad categories:
والكثير منها هي اعمال غير قتالية .. تقع ضمن تصنيفين
active engagement with ethnic rivalries and religious beliefs
المشاركة الفعالة مع الخصومات العرقية والمعتقدات الدينية
and fair, transparent economic development
وشفافية وعدالة التنمية الاقتصادية
and provisioning of services.
وتقديم الخدمات
I don't know about this, but this is what I can decipher from this diagram
أنا لست خبيراً في هذا المجال.. ولكن هذا ما استنتجته من هذا المخطط
in 24 seconds.
خلال 24 ثانية ..
When you see a diagram like this, I don't want you to be afraid.
عندما ترى مخططا مثل هذا .. لا تخف
I want you to be excited. I want you to be relieved.
بل تحمس .. واشعر بالارتياح
Because simple answers may emerge.
لان الاجوبة البسيطة سوف تكون بين يديك ..
We're discovering in nature that simplicity often lies
فقد اكتشفنا .. ان البساطة عادة تقع
on the other side of complexity.
على الطرف الاخر من التشعب المعقد ..
So for any problem, the more you can zoom out and embrace complexity,
لذا في اي مشكلة تواجهك .. كلما عدت خطوة او اثنتين الى الوراء .. لكي تصل الى الشبكة المتشعبة جداً
the better chance you have of zooming in
ستسهل عملية وصولك الى الحلول من اذا بقيت تنظر ضمن نطاق المشكلة
on the simple details that matter most.
وضمن تلك التفاصيل الصغيرة المتعلقة بها
Thank you.
شكراً لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)